

ENCRYPTO, Department of Computer Science of Technical University of Darmstadt, Germany

□ (+49) 1625122156 | 🗷 suresh@encrypto.cs.tu-darmstadt.de | 🏕 www.ajithsuresh.qithub.io | 🛅 ajithsuresh | 💆 @Ajith\_Suresh92 | 🕿 Ajith Suresh

"Be weird. Be random. Be who you are. Because you never know who would love the person you hide."

### Research Interests

My research focuses on cryptography and information security, emphasising efficient and secure protocols for problems in the area of Multi-party Computation (MPC). My current focus is on MPC for privacy-preserving services on the internet and in the area of Machine Learning. The topics of cryptography I have been interested in so far include MPC, Verifiable Secret Sharing, Oblivious Transfer, Byzantine Agreement and Broadcast, Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning.

#### Education

#### Indian Institute of Science (IISc)

PH. D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2021

Specialization: Secure Multi-party Computation (MPC)

- Thesis Title: MPCLeague: Robust MPC Platform for Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning
- Advisor: Prof. Arpita Patra
- Research Group: Cryptography and Information Security (CrIS)
- CGPA: 9 / 10 (First Class with Distinction)

#### Indian Institute of Science (IISc)

M.Tech. (Research) in Computer Science

- Specialization: Secure Multi-party Computation (MPC)
- Thesis Title: Fast Actively Secure OT Extension for Short Secrets
- · Advisor: Prof. Arpita Patra
- Research Group: Cryptography and Information Security (CrIS)
- CGPA: 6.83 / 8 (First Class with Distinction)

B.TECH IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

#### **College of Engineering, Trivandrum (CET)**

Thesis Title: Proximity-based Sentiment Analysis with Contextual Phrase Polarity

CGPA: 8.81 / 10 (First Class with Distinction)

# **Professional Experience**

#### Technical University (TU) of Darmstadt

Germany POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCH IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Oct. 2021 - Present

- Specialization: Privacy-preserving Services On the Internet (PSOTI)
- · Advisor: Prof. Thomas Schneider
- Research Group: Cryptography and Privacy Engineering (ENCRYPTO)

### Technical University (TU) of Darmstadt

Darmstadt, Germany Nov. 2019

Bengaluru, India

Aug. 2014 - Jun. 2017

Trivandrum, India

Jul. 2010 - Apr. 2014

RESEARCH INTERN

- Research work under the joint guidance of Thomas Schneider and Arpita Patra.
- The project aimed at improving the efficiency of secure two-party computation.
- Resulted in work titled "ABY2.0: Improved Mixed-Protocol Secure Two-Party Computation" which got accepted to USENIX Security Symposium'21.

#### **Amazon Development Centre**

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT ENGINEER (SDE) INTERN

Bangalore, India

Jul. 2013 - Aug. 2013

· Worked on the project titled "Increase the registered and subscribed user base at Amazon" under the mentorship of Bhanu Pratap Singh in the International Expansion (Junglee Traffic) Team.

**FEBRUARY 8, 2022** AJITH SURESH · CURRICULUM VITAE

### **Publications**

Publications in cryptography usually order authors alphabetically (using surnames) and conferences are more common than journals. I am the primary author for publications marked with †.

- 1. Nishat Koti, Arpita Patra, Rahul Rachuri and Ajith Suresh. *Tetrad: Actively Secure 4PC for Secure Training and Inference*<sup>†</sup>. In 29th Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS'22) (CORE rank- A\*) Full version: ia.cr/2021/755
- Arpita Patra, Thomas Schneider, Ajith Suresh and Hossein Yalame. SynCirc: Efficient Synthesis of Depth-Optimized Circuits for Secure Computation. In IEEE International Symposium on Hardware Oriented Security and Trust (HOST'21) Full version: ia.cr/2021/1153
- 3. Nishat Koti, Mahak Pancholi, Arpita Patra and Ajith Suresh. SWIFT: Super-fast and Robust Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning<sup>†</sup>. In 30th USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX'21) (CORE rank- A\*)
  Full version: ia.cr/2020/592
- Arpita Patra, Thomas Schneider, Ajith Suresh and Hossein Yalame. ABY2.0: Improved Mixed-Protocol Secure Two-Party Computation<sup>†</sup>. In 30th USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX'21) (CORE rank- A\*) Full version: ia.cr/2020/1225
- 5. Arpita Patra and Ajith Suresh. *BLAZE: Blazing Fast Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning*<sup>†</sup>. In 27th Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS'20) (CORE rank- A\*)
  Full version: ia.cr/2020/042
- Harsh Chaudhari, Rahul Rachuri and Ajith Suresh. Trident: Efficient 4PC Framework for Privacy Preserving Machine Learning<sup>†</sup>.
   In 27th Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS'20) (CORE rank- A\*)
   Full version: ia.cr/2019/1315
- 7. Megha Byali, Harsh Chaudhari, Arpita Patra and Ajith Suresh. *FLASH: Fast and Robust Framework for Privacy-preserving Machine Learning*. In 20th Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (PETS'20) (CORE rank- A) Full version: ia.cr/2019/1365
- Harsh Chaudhari, Ashish Choudhury, Arpita Patra and Ajith Suresh. ASTRA: High Throughput 3PC over Rings with Application to Secure Prediction<sup>†</sup>. In ACM Conference on Cloud Computing Security Workshop (ACM CCSW'19) Full version: ia.cr/2019/429
- 9. Arpita Patra, Pratik Sarkar and Ajith Suresh. Fast Actively Secure OT Extension for Short Secrets<sup>†</sup>. In 24th Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS'17) (CORE rank- A\*)
  Full version: ia.cr/2016/940

# **Workshops / Posters**

- 1. Nishat Koti, Shravani Patil, Arpita Patra and Ajith Suresh.. MPClan: Protocol Suite for Privacy-Conscious Computations. In NDSS'22 (Poster)
- 2. Nishat Koti, Arpita Patra, Rahul Rachuri and Ajith Suresh. *Tetrad: Actively Secure 4PC for Secure Training and Inference*. In PPML'21 (ACM CCS'21)

Full version: ia.cr/2021/755

- 3. Arpita Patra, Thomas Schneider, Ajith Suresh and Hossein Yalame. *ABY2.0: Improved Mixed-Protocol Secure Two-Party Computation*. In PriML'21 (NeurIPS'21), In PPML'21 (ACM CCS'21), In PPML'21 (CRYPTO'21)
  Full version: ia.cr/2020/1225
- 4. Nishat Koti, Arpita Patra and Ajith Suresh. MPCLeague: Robust and Efficient Mixed-protocol Framework for 4-party Computation. In IEEE S&P'21 (Poster), In DPML'21 (ICLR'21)

Poster: https://www.ieee-security.org/TC/SP2021/downloads/poster/poster25.pdf Full version: dp-ml.github.io/2021-workshop-ICLR/files/9.pdf

- 5. Nishat Koti, Mahak Pancholi, Arpita Patra and Ajith Suresh. SWIFT: Super-fast and Robust Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning. In ARCS'22 (Symposium), In DPML'21 (ICLR'21), In PriML/PPML'20 (NeurIPS'20)
  Full version: ia.cr/2020/592
- 6. Harsh Chaudhari, Ashish Choudhury, Arpita Patra and Ajith Suresh. ASTRA: High Throughput 3PC over Rings with Application to Secure Prediction. In PPML'19 (ACM CCS'19)

Full version: ia.cr/2019/429

### **Preprints**

 Nishat Koti, Shravani Patil, Arpita Patra and Ajith Suresh. MPClan: Protocol Suite for Privacy-Conscious Computations. Under Submission

# **Awards, Scholarships and Achievements**.

- 1. Nominated for the Schmidt Science Fellows 2022 program for post-doctoral research (one among a group of 350 highly accomplished candidates, nominated from 83 of the world's leading universities and institutes).
- 2. Represented country India in the "Window to the World" session at the 8th Heidelberg Laureate Forum.
- 3. Selected as one among 225 young researchers to participate in the 8th Heidelberg Laureate Forum.
- 4. Recipient of Google PhD Fellowship 2019 (one among 53 researchers around the globe).
- 5. Organiser of Secure Multi-Party Computation: Theory and Practice Workshop at Indian Institute of Science (IISc) from 19th to 22nd January, 2020.
- 6. Received travel grant to attend Privacy Preserving Machine Learning Workshop, CCS 2019, London.
- 7. Received travel grant to attend Workshop: Theory and Practice of Secure Multiparty Computation 2016, Aarhus University, Denmark.
- 8. Secured All India Rank of 807 with a score of 688 in GATE 2014 among (approximately) 1,55,190 students in India.
- 9. Ministry of Human Resource and Development (MHRD) Scholarship for Postgraduate education, India.
- 10. Best Outgoing student in Computer Science and Engineering (P Rathnaswamy Memorial Endowment) for the year 2014.
- 11. First prize in Coding Competition, CODESTORM, conducted by IEEE Computer Society (March 2013).
- 12. Received Ashok Leyland "ALL THE BEST" Scholarship for graduate studies, India (February 2011).
- 13. Recipient of Federal Bank Hormis Memorial Foundation Scholarship for graduate studies, India (2010-11).
- 14. Recipient of Indian Oil Education Scholarship for graduate education, India (2010-11).
- 15. Received Central Sector Scholarship by Department of Higher Education (MHRD) for graduate studies, India (2010).
- 16. Achieved a rank of 629 in Kerala Engineering Entrance (KEAM 2010) among (approximately) 100949 students.
- 17. Received Malayala Manorama Merit Scholarship (February 2008).
- 18. Received prize at CMS Math Prodigy Hunt 2009, organized by Centre for Research in Mathematics.
- 19. Participated in 20th Kerala Science Congress, Trivandrum (January 2008).
- 20. Participated in Youth Parliament Competition under the auspices of the Institute of Parliamentary Affairs, Government of Kerala.

## Talks and Presentations

- 1. August 2021. SWIFT: Super-fast and Robust Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning. 30th USENIX Security Symposium, Virtual Event.
- 2. June 2021. SWIFT: Super-fast and Robust Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning. CNI Networks Seminar Series, Centre for Networked Intelligence, Virtual Event, India.
- 3. May 2021. MPC for small population with applications to Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning. EECS Research Students Symposium 2021, Virtual Event, India.
- 4. May 2021. MPCLeague: Robust and Efficient Mixed-protocol Framework for 4-party Computation. Distributed and Private Machine Learning (DPML), ICLR Workshop 2021, Virtual Event.
- 5. February 2021. *ABY2.0: Improved Mixed-Protocol Secure Two-Party Computation*. 15th Academic Research and Careers for Students Symposium (ARCS) 2021, Virtual Event, India.
- 6. February 2021. *BLAZE: Blazing Fast Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning*. 15th Academic Research and Careers for Students Symposium (ARCS) 2021, Virtual Event, India.

- 7. July 2020. MPC MEETS ML: Efficient Privacy Preserving Machine Learning Techniques. EECS Research Students Symposium 2020, Virtual Event, India.
- 8. July 2020. MPC MEETS ML: Efficient Privacy Preserving Machine Learning Techniques. International Symposium on Current Trends in Research and Innovation (ISCTRI'20), Virtual Event, india.
- 9. February 2020. *BLAZE: Blazing Fast Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning*. The Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS) 2020, San Diego, USA.
- 10. February 2020. *Trident: Efficient 4PC Framework for Privacy Preserving Machine Learning*. The Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS) 2020, San Diego, USA.
- 11. February 2020. ASTRA: High Throughput 3PC over Rings with Application to Secure Prediction. 14th Inter-Research-Institute Student Seminar in Computer Science (IRISS) 2020, IIT Gandhinagar.
- 12. January 2020. MPC MEETS ML: Efficient Privacy Preserving Machine Learning Techniques. Hitachi-IISc Project Review, IISc, India.
- 13. January 2020. MPC MEETS ML: Efficient Privacy Preserving Machine Learning Techniques. Secure Multi-Party Computation: Theory and Practice Workshop, IISc, India.
- 14. November 2019. ASTRA: High Throughput 3PC over Rings with Application to Secure Prediction. TU Darmstadt, Germany.
- 15. March 2019. MPC MEETS ML: High Throughput Secure ML Prediction. Amazon Project Review, IISc, India.
- 16. August 2018. Cryptography Basics. QIP STC on Foundations of Cryptography, IISc, India.
- 17. April 2017. Fast Actively Secure OT Extension for Short Secrets. EECS Symposium, IISc, India.
- 18. February 2017. Fast Actively Secure OT Extension for Short Secrets. The Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS) 2017, San Diego, USA.
- 19. February 2016. *Oblivious Transfer (OT) and OT Extensions*. Workshops on Cryptography, organized as a part of Information Security Education and Awareness Project Phase II, IISc.
- 20. February 2016. *Two party computation (GMW construction)*. Workshops on Cryptography, organized as a part of Information Security Education and Awareness Project Phase II, IISc.
- 21. February 2016. *Message Authentication Codes*. Workshops on Cryptography, organized as a part of Information Security Education and Awareness Project Phase II, IISc.
- 22. January 2016. *Efficient Actively Secure Oblivious Transfer Extension*. 10th Inter-Research-Institute Student Seminar in Computer Science (IRISS) 2016, Technopark, Trivandrum, Kerala.

### **Research Events**

**FEBRUARY 8, 2022** 

- 1. August 2021. 8th Heidelberg Laureate Forum. Heidelberg (Virtual Event), Germany.
- 2. August 2021. The 30th USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX) 2021. (Virtual Event).
- 3. May 2021. EECS Research Students Symposium 2021. Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore (Virtual Event), India.
- 4. May 2021. Distributed and Private Machine Learning (DPML), ICLR Workshop 2021. (Virtual Event).
- 5. February 2021. 15th Academic Research and Careers for Students Symposium (ARCS) 2021. PSG College of Technology, Coimbatore (Virtual Event), India.
- 6. July 2020. EECS Research Students Symposium 2020. Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore (Virtual Event), India.
- 7. July 2020. International Symposium on Current Trends in Research and Innovation (ISCTRI'20). CHRIST University, Pune Lavasa Campus (Virtual Event), India.
- 8. February 2020. The 27th Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS) 2020. San Diego, USA.
- 9. February 2020. 14th Inter-Research-Institute Student Seminar in Computer Science (IRISS) 2020. Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Gandhinagar, India.
- 10. January 2020. Secure Multi-Party Computation: Theory and Practice 2020. Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore, India.
- 11. November 2019. The 26th ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS) 2019. London, United Kingdom.

AJITH SURESH · CURRICULUM VITAE

12. December 2017. 18th International Conference on Cryptology (INDOCRYPT) 2017. The Institute of Mathematical Sciences (IMSc), Chennai, India.

- 13. March 2017. NMI Workshop on Secure Multiparty Computation. Indian Institute of Technology (IIT), Bomaby, India.
- 14. February 2017. The 24th Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS) 2017. San Diego, USA.
- 15. June 2016. Theory and Practice of Secure Multiparty Computation Workshop (TPMPC) 2016. Aarhus university, Denmark.
- 16. January 2016. 10th Inter-Research-Institute Student Seminar in Computer Science (IRISS) 2016. Trivandrum, India.

### **Scientific Service**

- 1. Acted as external reviewer for
  - 2022 EUROCRYPT, ACM CCS, IEEE TDSC (Journal)
  - · 2021 ACM CCS, PODC, ITC, CRYPTO
  - 2020 ASIACRYPT, IEEE TIFS (Journal)
  - · 2019 CRYPTO, ASIACRYPT, TCC, PKC
  - 2018 EUROCRYPT, ASIACRYPT
  - 2017 ASIACRYPT, PKC
  - 2016 CRYPTO
- 2. Organiser of EECS Research Students Symposium 2017 at Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore, India.

# **Teaching Experience**

#### Indian Institute of Science (IISc)

Bengaluru, India

CSA E0 312: Secure Computation (Teaching Assistant)

Jan. - Apr.'17, Aug. - Dec.'19

- Instructor: Dr. Arpita Patra
- Department of Computer Science and Automation (CSA), IISc.
- Gave course lectures, mentoring in course projects, evaluation.

#### Indian Institute of Science (IISc)

Bengaluru, India

CSA E0 235: CRYPTOGRAPHY (TEACHING ASSISTANT)

Jan. - Apr.'16, Aug. - Dec.'19

- Instructor: Dr. Arpita Patra
- Department of Computer Science and Automation (CSA), IISc.
- · Conducted weekly tutorial sessions discussing questions from the areas covered in the course, evaluation of exam sheets.

### Indian Institute of Science (IISc)

Bengaluru, India

Aug. - Dec.'18

UG E101: ALGORITHMS AND PROGRAMMING (TEACHING ASSISTANT)

- Instructors: Satish Govindarajan and Viraj Kumar
- · Undergraduate (UG) Department, IISc.
- · Conducted weekly coding tutorial sessions, evaluation of assignments.

# **Projects**

#### **College of Engineering, Trivandrum**

Trivandrum, India

**BTECH MAIN PROJECT** 

BTECH MINI PROJECT

Jan. - Mar.'14,

- Title: Proximity based Sentiment Analysis with Contextual Phrase Polarity.
- · This aims to find the sentiment or mood of a given text segment (or review) using word proximity.

### **College of Engineering, Trivandrum**

Trivandrum, India

Jan.'13,

• Title: Student Tracker - A complete student management system.

Trivandrum, India

• A tool for managing the student database of a college using Java front end and Oracle back end.

### **College of Engineering, Trivandrum**

OTHER PROJECTS

- A project on Road Safety using mobile controlled speed governor in association with IEEE.
- · A project on android device that can convert a base line video to normal high quality video for live streaming, in association with IET and Aceware Technology Ltd.



**Programming** C/C++, Java, Javascript, Python

**DevOps** AWS, Docker **DBMS** Oracle, SQL

WebHTML5, CSS3, jQuery, JSPToolsNetBeans, Eclipse, MFX

# Personal Data\_\_\_\_

**Born** 24th April 1992 in Kerala, India

**Citizenship** Indian **Marital Status** Married

**Languages** Malayalam (mother tongue), English, Hindi, Tamil

**Interests** Photography, Badminton, Cycling